Guide to the David Wagstaff Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
David Wagstaff collection
1810-1935
MS 541
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
The collection of logbooks and ship's papers gathered by David Wagstaff, plus correspondence and reports concerning the Canadian salmon industry and student notebooks of Philip Kearny (1815-1862) and Thomas Richmond (d. 1859) when they were students at Columbia.
Wagstaff, David, 1882-1951
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of David Wagstaff and the Wagstaff estate.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
The logbooks and equipage inventories are also available on microfilm as part of Hist. MSS Film 21.
Biographical / Historical
David Wagstaff: broker and sportsman; B.A. Harvard, 1905; partner in the N.Y.C. brokerage firm of Dominick & Dominick, 1915-1929; collected sporting books, paintings, and prints which he later donated to the University of Virginia and Yale University.
Scope and Contents
The collection of logbooks and ship's papers gathered by David Wagstaff, plus correspondence and reports concerning the Canadian salmon industry and student notebooks of Philip Kearny (1815-1862) and Thomas Richmond (d. 1859) when they were students at Columbia.
Salmon canning industry -- Canada; Shipping; Canada -- Industries; New Bedford (Mass.) -- History; Logs (records); Ships' papers; Kearny, Philip, 1815-1862; Richmond, Thomas, d. 1859; Columbia University
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  For a full description of the logbooks or inventories of equipage and of the voyages of the vessels listed below, see the register for Whaling and Sealing Logs, Hist. Mss. Film 21.
  - Logs
    - Commodore Decatur (ship) of New Bedford, Mass., 1833 May 20-1835 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - E. Corning (bark) of New Bedford, Mass., 1866 July 10-1869 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - James Allen (bark) of New Bedford, Mass., 1877 September 18-1878 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Nautilus (bark) of New Bedford, Mass., 1874 August 25-1877 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Julian (ship) of New Bedford, Mass., 1858 October 1-1868 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Louisiana (ship) of New Bedford, Mass., 1850 August 15-1853 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mattapoisett (bark) of Westport, Mass., 1871 June 21-1872 August 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - F.H. Moore (brig) of Boston, Mass., 1873 May 12-1874 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Pioneer (bark) of New Bedford, Mass., 1875 June 6-1876 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Rousseau (ship) of New Bedford, Mass., 1837 November 8-1840 December 10 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Vesta (brig) of Edgartown, Mass., 1841 May 18-1842 October 20 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Inventories of equipage
    - Barbara (bark) of New York, New York, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Camillus (ship) of [?], 1837 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Henry (ship) of [?], 1834 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, reports and other materials relating to the salmon industry of eastern Canada, 1930-35, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Three lecture notebooks of Philip Kearny (1815-1862) made while a student at Columbia University, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Lecture notebook of Thomas Richmond (-1859) made while a student at Columbia University, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Poetry notebook of Frederic H. Russell of Dartmouth, Mass., 1871-1872 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Logs (Note: the logbooks and equipage inventories are also available on microfilm as part of Hist. MSS Film 21.)
    - George (ship) of Dartmouth, Mass., 1832 April 2-1834 March 11 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Joseph Meigs (ship) of New Bedford, Mass., 1850 October 22-1854 August 1 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Montpelier (ship) of New Bedford, Mass., 1844 September 22-1847 July 30 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - William Baker (ship) of Warren, R.I., 1834 August 13-1836 February 10 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Letter to Capt. Frederic Barnard of Ship Rebecca from Charles, Samuel and George Enderby, plus a list of expenses, 1810 February 27 (Box 4)
  - Two letters to Thomas Westwood, London and Weybridge from Henry Cholmondeley Pennell (1837-1915), 1864 June 15 [1865] October 2 (Box 4)